<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the iust causes of his Maiesties proceeding against those ministers, who are now lying in prison, attainted of high treason. Set foorth by his Maiesties Counsell of his kingdome of Scotland</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852085</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17390</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17390)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the iust causes of his Maiesties proceeding against those ministers, who are now lying in prison, attainted of high treason. Set foorth by his Maiesties Counsell of his kingdome of Scotland</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>Haddington, Thomas Hamilton, Earl of, 1563-1637, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Sir Thomas Hamilton, Earl of Haddington.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  James VI, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:17390:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17390:1"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION <hi>of the iust cauſes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties</hi> proceeding againſt thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who are now lying in priſon, attainted of high treaſon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S his Maieſties fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care hath euer bene ſo great towards his people and louing Subiects, as he hath not onely bene care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to gouerne them by iuſt and aequitable Lawes, but likewiſe hath euer had a ſpeciall reſpect to the true and right information of their minds as touching all his publique Actions and proceedings: So for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he hath euer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Declaration and Proclamation inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted and explained to all his louing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects his true intention and ſinceritie of his meaning, that thereby his Subiects know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his will, and of the grounds moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him thereunto, being ioyned to their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17390:2"/>
duetifull and naturall inclination of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a reuerent loue together with a feare to offend, might bee continually encreaſed and nouriſhed in their hearts, their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not proceeding of a naked feare, but from a feare mixed and ſtrengthened with loue for good reaſons, and founded vpon a good conſcience and cleare knowledge of the trueth.</p>
            <p>And as this his Maieſties fatherly care hath euer ſince his maioritie of yeeres moſt clearely appeared in all the points of his Highneſſe gouernment in this his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Scotland: So now vpon that late occaſion of the Rebellious and traiterous misbehauiour of ſome particular Miniſters within this Kingdome, his Maieſtie conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing his former louing cuſtome towards his Subiects, hath thought conuenient to ſet out this preſent declaration for ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Highneſſe Subiects of all rankes, concerning his Maieſties courſe and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in this caſe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe he hath iuſt reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that if any of whatſoeuer eſtate or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17390:2"/>
of his Maieſties Subiects bee ſo vndu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, as to haue any ſcruple of the Iuſtice and neceſsitie of his Highneſſe proceedings herein, it doeth onely proceed of ignorance or miſtaking the trueth of his Highneſſe actions: His Maieſtie is therefore moued to thinke that there can be no ſo good and ſure way for true information of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, as to ſet downe vnto them the true ſtate of the queſtion, together with all that hath followed and riſen thereupon, The miſtaking whereof (his Maieſtie doth aſſure himſelfe) is the onely cauſe from whence all ſcruples in ſome mens hearts (if any be) doe ſpring and proceed.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie for the three or foure laſt yeeres together before his departure out of this Kingdome, being caried with a moſt ardent Zeale and earneſt Affection to the aduancement of Gods glory and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Religion preſently profeſt, neuer ſpared to vndergoe in his owne moſt Royall and ſacred Perſon almoſt intolerable paines and faſhery for preuenting of all diſorders and corruptions which crept into the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17390:3"/>
Church, and for ſetting downe and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing ſuch a ſolide and comely forme of gouernment as might be able to preſerue the puritie of our Profeſsion, and procure the eſtabliſhing of a ſolide Peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Church. And for that cauſe he was euer preſent at all the frequent Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and Aſſemblies of the Miniſterie in this kingdome. And if his Maieſties affaires and other incident occaſions had bene ſuch as he could not bee able to keepe the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed place and dyet to the which hee had called the aſſembly, his Highneſſe did euer carefully prorogate and continue it, to ſuch other time and place as his leaſure might permit him to be preſent at the ſaid meeting. And as his Maieſtie by thoſe his traueils had already put this our Church in a good beginning and forwardneſſe of a good order and frame: ſo he no way doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, but if he had made any longer ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, he would with Gods aſsiſtance haue brought it by this time to a reaſonable and expected perfection. But ſuch is the malicious enuy of the euill diſpoſed ſort,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17390:3"/>
grudging at the progreſſe of any good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that ſome of thoſe Miniſters who euer had bene hinderers and croſſers of that good worke as farre as they durſt, euen in his Maieſties owne preſence, conceyting with themſelues, that now in his Highneſſe abſence from this Countrey (with whom they ſuppoſed all memory and regard both of Church and Common wealth had bene altogether forgotten and neglected) and that by reaſon of the aſsignment of a day in the moneth of Iuly laſt paſt, for keeping of an aſſembly (betwixt the appointment whereof and the time it ſelfe, interuened that moſt happy and neceſſary cauſe of his Highnes going into England) they thought a very fit occaſion was offered to them for proſequution of their intentions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they endeuoured, to the vttermoſt of their power, to reuerſe and ouerthrow all thoſe good orders and godly Conſtitutions formerly concluded for keeping of good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their Church, And partly by ſecret ſuggeſtion of falſe calumnies to the ſimple and ignorant, and by plotting and combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17390:4"/>
with thoſe of more turbulent ſpirits, who knowing that their owne inhabilitie would impede them to be any way prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, made choiſe with the Camel to drinke in muddy water, and by perturbing of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters rather to ouerthrow all good order, then that by ſetling of the Church-gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the vertues of others, and their vices and imperfections ſhould be clearely diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and diſtinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>Therefore to aſſure themſelues the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the compaſsing of this their deſſeigne, they ſpared no time, nor left no meane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſayed to preoccupy mens opinions, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate their votes, and to make vp a ſtrong Faction againſt the meeting of that aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, thereby fully intending to bring the eſtate of this Church to a moſt euident con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſorder.</p>
            <p>Vpon ſome notice of the which miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous Plots and Machinations, his Maieſtie conſidering, that his abſence from that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture meeting of Aſſembly, and the neere approching of the time appointed for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereof were embraced by thoſe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17390:4"/>
ſpirits as fit opportunities and good occaſions offered vnto them ſo to ouer-rule that matter by thus preparing and packing vp of Votes beforehand, that howſoeuer the better ſort ſhould oppoſe themſelues thereunto, yet they ſhould be ſure to make the eſtate of this Church without any rule at all: And therefore his moſt excellent Maieſtie continuing in that fatherly care which hee euer caried to this Church and Realme, by his Highnes Letter ſigned with his owne hand, directed to the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the generall Aſſembly, ſignified vnto them his ſpeciall Pleaſure and will, That that meeting and aſſembly appointed to haue beene the ſecond of Iuly now laſt paſt, ſhould be deſerted; and that no new Indiction ſhould be made either of day or place without his Maieſties conſent. And thereafter hee deſired, that ſome of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and alſo ſome of the beſt, wiſeſt, and moſt religious of the Miniſtery, ſhould repaire towards his Maieſtie with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient ſpeed, That his Highneſſe with their aduice might not onely reſolue vpon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17390:5"/>
all ſuch grounds as were fitteſt and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for the ſetling of the Peace of the Church, but might alſo appoint ſome fit and conuenient day and place for holding of a new Aſſembly. Vpon the receipt of the which Letter, the ſaid Commiſsioners of the Aſſembly, by their Miſsiues directed vnto all the Presbyteries of the Kingdome, certified them of his Maieſties pleaſure and will, concerning the deſerting of that Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; Willing them that they ſhould not in any caſe ſend their Commiſsioners to keep that day formerly appointed, and now by his Maieſties warrant deſerted, but that they ſhould expect the appointing of a new day and place for keeping of an Aſſembly. But ſo farre were ſome of the Miniſterie from making any accompt of his Maieſties dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (a thing moſt deteſtable in any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, much more in any of the Miniſterie, whoſe Doctrine, Life, and whole Actions ought to be Lanternes to others of all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience to their Prince) as by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in plaine contempt thereof, moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiouſly they conuened at <hi>Aberdene.</hi> And
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17390:5"/>
being guiltie to themſelues of their owne inhabilitie, vnworthineſſe, and ſmall giftes, conioyned with a bad inclination, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in deſpaire that in doing good they ſhould euer become memorable, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled with a burning deſire of vaine glory, reſolued by ouerthrowing the gouernment of this Church, and by inducing all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereinto, to make themſelues (at leaſt for their euill) famous with that ſometime burner of the Temple at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the aduertiſement of his Maieſties Pleaſure and will for the deſerting of the ſaid Aſſembly ſent by the Commiſsioners, was dutifully receiued and willingly obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the whole Presbyteries almoſt of this Kingdome; Yet ſome fewe Miniſters (not exceeding the number of eighteene or nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene perſons at moſt, ouer-ruling the reſt of their poore brethren of their eight or nine ſeuerall Preſbyteries, ouer whome, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their ſaid brethrens ſimplicitie, and their owne craftineſſe, they had got in time paſt very much aduantage, &amp; had them in a manner tyed to their girdles to conſent to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17390:6"/>
any thing whatſoeuer) ſo brought it to paſſe, as by their procurement, the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Maieſties pleaſure was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and they themſelues choſen Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to that Meeting, which by his Highneſſe commandement was deſerted.</p>
            <p>And wee of his Maieſties Counſell fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the preſumption of theſe fewe (howſoeuer in words profeſsing, yet in their deedes directly impugning his Maieſties Authority Royall, vnder a coloured pretext of their zeale to Religion, which alas is now moſt deteſtably abuſed as an ordinarie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and excuſe for euery treaſon and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe) thus conuening without regard of his Maieſties command made to the contrary, might be a dangerous preparatiue to the whole Eſtate, conſidering that thoſe who ſhould be the teachers of others, were now become the onely violators of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their moſt gracious and religious Souereigne: Therefore wee directed Sir <hi>Alexander Strayton</hi> of <hi>Lawrenston</hi> Knight to the ſaid Borough of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> with ſpeciall warrant and commandement to prohibite
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17390:6"/>
and diſcharge that fewe number of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters from conuening at all; and alſo by a ſpeciall Miſsiue written vnto them, wee ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified his Maieſties pleaſure concerning the deſerting of that Diet. Notwithſtanding the publication of which charge at the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Croſſe of <hi>Aberdene</hi> the day before their meeting, they being all in Towne, and of the deliuerie of our Letter; the next day thereafter they being all conuened, were ſo farre from carying any reſpect to the charge which was directed and executed in his Maieſties name, or to the Miſsiue ſent from vs, or to the bearer being his Maieſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioner in Church affaires; as the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contemned directly, the Letter was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially anſwered, and the bearer (whoſe preſence at all their doings was ordinarily moſt neceſſarie) was neuertheleſſe at this time excluded foorth of dores all the time of their keeping that Aſſembly till the end thereof.</p>
            <p>A particular relation of all which circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances being faithfully made to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, his Highneſſe tooke occaſion with his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17390:7"/>
owne hand to pen a Declaration, whereby not onely all pretext of excuſe or defence which may be pretended by theſe Miniſters is clearely refuted, but alſo their proud con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and diſobedience is made ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, as we do fully aſſure our ſelues, no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of doubt will remaine with any who is not peruerſly preoccupyed to diſtruſt all veritie.</p>
            <p>The Declaration wee haue preſumed to inſert in this place, as it came from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie himſelfe, and is this.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17390:7"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <p>BEcauſe this vnruly handfull of Miniſters that made the faſhion of keeping of this pretended Aſsemblie, together with their Aſſociates and Allowers, do ſo much bragge of the equitie of their cauſe, and wilfully maintaine that the ground of their proceedings was most iuſt and neceſsarie, and if any errour was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it was onely in forme, which proceeded out of neceſsitie, in reſpect of the vnlawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of their liberty, as they alledge: we haue herefore thought good to ſet downe most ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly and ſhortly the vine Anatomie of their actions, and the true ſtate of their cauſe; to the intent that power being ioyned to reaſon (as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath bene our conſtant forme of proceeding) in all our gouernment, their nakedneſſe being truely diſcouered, the due puniſhment to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon them may the better appeare in their owne colour as well as their tranſgreſsion. And therefore whereas they bragge of warrant of conſcience, warrant of lawe, the due obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their owne cuſtomes and liberties, and the reſpect of the weale of the Church, as the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17390:8"/>
true Motiues of this their vnruly and ſeditious contempt; The contrary of all theſe ſhall bee made clearely to appeare.</p>
                        <p>And first for warrant of conſcience for their generall Aſsemblie, which they terme the Counſell of God, in the whole olde Teſtament they will not claime to any warrant of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſemblie; And in the whole newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they can alleage no warrant for generall Aſſemblies, but that conuention of the Apostles at Ieruſalem mentioned in the Acts of Apoſtles, which indeed was an vniuerſall counſell of the whole Church, and no wayes like to a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Scots generall Aſſemblie: and therefore they must leaue the Scripture, and haue recourſe to the example of the Primitiue Church for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of particular Nationall Counſels, To which warrant we are aſſured that they will be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to claime, in regard many Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſuch as Veſtiments, Croſſe and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, will bee found in the ſame Primitiue Church which they do vtterly abhorre. And ſince the Emperours (how ſoone they became Chriſtians) had the onely vndoubted authoritie in their perſons of conuening generall Counſels,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17390:8"/>
which neuer was taken from them while the Pope aſcended to the height of his abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; how much leſse ought that authoritie bee denied to a Chriſtian Monarch in the aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a Nationall Councell of his owne Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, who hath farre greater and iuſter Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer his owne people, then any vſurping Emperor could claime ouer the face of the whole Earth? And if they will alleadge the new pureſt writers of our dayes, profeſſours of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That by their miſsiue Letter both to the Prince, and State of the Church of Scotland, they haue wiſhed the holding of frequent Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies in that Countrey (but alwayes by the kings permiſsion) as a meane whereby both do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and diſcipline might be maintained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbance, and much good thereby procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Church of God; yet theſe very argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theirs doe declare, that they onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade it by way of aduiſe as a thing very conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and did not ſet it downe as a rule of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and an infallible law.</p>
                        <p>Next as to the warrant of our Law in that kingdom, It is firſt to be generally obſerued, that no priuiledge that any King giues to one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17390:9"/>
body or ſtate within the kingdome of conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; conſulting among themſelues, is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to bee <hi>Priuatiuè</hi> giuen vnto them, and ſo the King therby depriuing himſelfe of his own power and prerogatiue, but onely to be giuen <hi>Cumulatiuè</hi> vnto them (as the Lawyers call it) without any way denuding the King of his owne power and authority. As for an inſtance (which hath bene too frequent in all this Ile theſe yeeres past, ſauing the pleaſure of God) Euery Burgh Regall haue their owne times of publike mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates allowed vnto them by the Law, and the Kings priuilege: but when the plague happened in any of theſe townes, did not we by proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſcharge the holding of the mercate at that time for feare of infection, and yet thereby did no preiudice to their priuiledges, neither did any of them ineptly murmure, much leſſe enter into that high contempt as to ſay they would obey the Kings Lawes in keeping their priuiledges, and not the particular reſtraint thereof at that time for neceſſary cauſes?</p>
                        <p>And as to the nature of their particular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge in holding of aſſemblies, they haue in this their last pretended Aſſembly broken the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17390:9"/>
limitations of that priuiledge that is clearely ſet downe in the first Acte of the Parliament, in the <hi>92.</hi> yeere, which is the latest and clearest warrant for their Aſſemblie. For there it is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially prouided, That as wee giue them licence for holding of their Aſsemblies once in the yeere or ofter as occaſion ſhall require, (which proues that all their power onely proceeds from vs) So muſt it not bee conuened without our owne preſence or then of our Commiſsioner, nor no day nor place ſet downe for the next Aſſemblie but by Our or our Commiſsioners appoyntment, except we bee not pleaſed neither to goe in our owne perſon, neither to ſend any for aſsiſting the ſayd Aſſembly. And how theſe limitations haue bene obſerued by them at this time, let the world iudge, firſt in not onely refuſing the preſence of our Commiſsioner, but most contemptuouſly and iniuriouſly barring the doore vpon him, and next in ſetting downe the dyet of the next Aſſembly, without either his priuitie or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
                        <p>And as to the third point of their iuſtifying themſelues by the warrant of the conſtitution &amp; custome of their owne Church, we would know
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17390:10"/>
what warrant they haue for holding of a new aſsembly without the preſence either of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator of the last; or of the ordinarie clarke of the aſſembly; The Clark ſpecially at that inſtant being dwelling in the ſame towne where they conuened. For their cuſtome hath euer bene, that the moderator ſhould call for all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners name by name, ſhould ſee their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Presbyterie, ſhould giue them the lytis for election of a newe moderator, and make their names (the parties being remoued) freely to be voted among them; but firſt of all the moderator ought to preach vnto them, and out of the word of God teach them their duetie at that meeting. But as this their pretended Aſsembly was kept in contempt of our autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie royall: So had it (prayſed be God) no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the word of God, without the which order in their proceeding, we would know what might let as many ſundrie generall Aſſemblies to be conuened at one time in diuerſe places of that countrey, as there are ſeuerall numbers of ninteene miniſters through the countrey: And ſo there ſhould be at one inſtant farre moe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſemblies in Scotland one against ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17390:10"/>
then euer there was Popes in one time in our aduerſarie Church. And if they would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the ſtraitneſſe of theſe euill dayes (wherein they liue) compelled them to omit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe of their auncient and lowable cuſtomes, that cannot but imply a direct accuſation of our tyrannie, for which this anſwere may ſuffice, That beſides our knowen ſinceritie in religion and conſtant loue to do Iustice to all our people: They can neuer alledge that they did ſo much as to ſend a petition either to our ſelfe, or in reſpect of our abſence to our Counſell there, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of this Aſſembly. For whereas they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that this day was continued by vs and the Commiſsioners of the Church without affixing a new dyet; we thinke the leaſt they could haue done, had bene humbly to haue craued the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of a new dyet, and patiently to haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected either our anſwere or our Counſels there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, rather then by this their outrageous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to haue proclamed either our vniust per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of them, or elſe (which is the truth) their arrogant and ſeditious diſobedience.</p>
                        <p>And laſtly, how carefully they reſpected the weale of their Church in this courſe, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17390:11"/>
to the world: Firſt, by needleſſe irritating againſt them their ancient, lawfull, religious and moſt mercifull King, whereas they might haue come to their owne end by their mild behauiour and due obedience. And next by making as needleſſe a ſeparation betwixt all the reſt of their learned, wiſe, graue and duetifull bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and them, who for their parts are in this caſe according to their qualitie as farre lightlied and diſgraced by them, as we are diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. And thirdly, by bringing on a publike ſcandall hereby vpon their profeſſion, as rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious to ſo religious and iuſt a King, whereby the aduerſaries of our religion (who like roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lions goe about to watch ſuch opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) may fill their new bookes and pamphlets with ſuch ſcandalous memorials againſt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And lastly, what charitie they haue by this their behauiour vſed towards their puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane brethren in this countrey, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues may eaſily geſſe, hauing by this their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt done nothing elſe, but animated and ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs to the ſtraiter animaduerſion and order taking with them; lest otherwiſe, as they are both fauourers of one diſcipline, ſo they may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17390:11"/>
ſome day by their example (if they had as great libertie) giue proofe of their like diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and contempt of our authoritie.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>NOw leauing it to euery one to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue both the Patience and Pietie of a moſt puiſſant Prince; His Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that after ſo great a contempt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by ſo meane, baſe, and abiect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who were neuer any way remarkable as men of great gifts, but were ſpecially noted of too great a deſire to bee made fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, if by no other meanes, yet at leaſt by their troubling and ouerturning of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: And although his Maieſtie had moſt iuſt cauſe of offence againſt ſome of them for their great ouerſight in former time, and that others of them had moſt vndutifully in that ſame action made breach of ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made by them vnrequired, to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie himſelfe very fewe moneths before: Yet ſo ſuperabundant was his lenitie and patience towards them, that after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the contempt, they were not committed preſently, but ſuffered to ſtaie
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17390:12"/>
at home at their owne houſes: neither were they preſently brought to their anſwere; but his Maieſtie moſt patiently in hope of their repentance was pleaſed a long time to ſuperſede the ordinarie courſe of Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And herewithall his Maieſties Pietie doth moſt cleerely ſhine, that beeing euen ſince his infancie a moſt gratious nurſe-father of the Religion profeſſed, and protector of the profeſſors, but ſpecially of the Teachers of the ſame; And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the contempt committed was ſo hainous, as by the ordinarie courſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, his Maieſtie might preſently haue bin auenged of thoſe diſdainers of his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Royall commandements: yet ſo farre was his Maieſtie from any rigorous proceeding againſt them, as by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to the intent to recall them backe, who were now ſo farre aſtray out of the path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of obedience, (a moſt pittifull, yea a moſt abominable thing in a Miniſter) it pleaſed his ſacred Maieſtie moſt gratiouſly of himſelfe to ſet downe that former Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that vpon the view thereof, theſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17390:12"/>
Miniſters might ſee their offence, confeſſe their guiltineſſe, and craue pardon. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in howſoeuer ſome of them were euer all their life, and likewiſe at this time ſo ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that they could not be recalled by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lure; yet were ſixe or ſeuen of that number of nineteene which firſt conuened, ſo moued and touched with that open Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie made by that Declarator, of their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight, as in all humilitie before the Lords of his Maieſties Councell then preſent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting their great ſorrow for their offence, excuſing themſelues vpon their ignorance, and purging themſelues of all wilfulneſſe in that action, they beſought their Lordſhips to bee mediators at his Maieſties hands for a pardon to them. Who preſently vpon their humble ſubmiſſion (according as his Maieſtie had beene pleaſed to ſignifie his will and minde to his Councell) were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, and ſent home to their houſes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their charge and miniſterie ouer their owne flockes. So farre was his Maieſties heart from intending any rigour againſt any of that Profeſsion, as by the contrarie, by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17390:13"/>
his Maieſties preſent pardoning of them vpon their ſubmiſsion, it doeth manifeſtly appeare that his Highneſſe was farre more willing and readie to embrace their peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with clemencie, then they could bee capable to deſerue the ſame; imitating herein his great King the king of all kings, who neuer deſireth the death, but the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of the ſinner. And yet it is moſt true, that thoſe ſo diſmiſſed vpon their humble ſubmiſsion and repentance, were men of no leſſe gifts, but of farre greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, knowen good life and conuerſation, and nothing inferior to thoſe others which remaine ſtill obſtinate, but in vnquietneſſe of ſpirit, hautineſſe of minde, and deſire of breaking the Peace of the Church. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any further bee touched of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting before any Iudge, or that any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bee made how by their pertinacie of maintaining the firſt fault (beeing a moſt preſumptuous riot) they came next within the compaſſe of no leſſe offence then Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: it is not vnmeete that the very point of their firſt crime, for which they were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17390:13"/>
brought in queſtion, to anſwere before his Maieſties Counſel, were cleerely ſet downe, as well to refute thoſe vaine ſubterfuges of excuſes and pretexts they make for their obſtinacie, as to remooue from the godly, religious, and well diſpoſed Subiects, all ſcruple of any ſuch matter whereof thoſe miniſters and their fauorites by lying ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors would ſowe the ſeedes amongſt the ſimple ſort, whom they very well know, and wee often finde to be too credulous of euery falſe report.</p>
            <p>As therefore the keeping of a generall Aſſembly was not the matter in queſtion: ſo is it of veritie, that by this accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe diſobedient miniſters, there was nothing laid to their charge concerning the lawfulneſſe or vnlawfulneſſe of a generall Aſſembly, nor yet of the power and limits thereof; but that they had vnlawfully made a priuie Conuenticle, not onely directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant and againſt his Maieſtie and Counſels charges and direction, but euen as well againſt the continuall cuſtome and practiſe of the Church, as their preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17390:14"/>
which was well witneſſed by all the Presbyteries, abſtaining from directing any Commiſsioners thither, ſauing that ſmall number of Presbyteries already recited, whereof they were the Commiſsioners, for they not onely diſobeyed his Maieſties Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, who had diſcharged that time and place of meetings, but euen the will and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their owne Church, whoſe diſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to their proceeding, was not onely manifeſted by the Commiſsioners of the generall Aſsemblies letter, certifying all the Presbyteries of the deſerting of the ſaid Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, but alſo the Church did by their not ſending of Commiſsioners to that diet, cleerely demonſtrate their obedient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement and acquieſcing to his Maieſties wil in that behalfe, of whoſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and lawfull Authoritie in appointing or continuing the times and places of meeting of Aſſemblies they neuer doubted, beeing ſo often practiſed, (as is already rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) in his Maieſties owne perſon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be his prerogatiue by that ſame Acte of Parliament by which they are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17390:14"/>
warranted to keepe the ſaide Aſſemblies. And if thoſe Miniſters who ſtand ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in defence of th' aſſembly (which they muſt confeſſe hath onely warrant from that Statute in 92.) would conſider how farre the Prince may diſpoſe of the meetings of the Parliament it ſelfe, as either to prolong, haſten or deſert the meeting thereof; and beeing conuened, may diſmiſſe the ſame without doing any thing at all therein; What fooliſh prerogatiue and ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence is this (ſeeing they muſt needes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelues ſubalteme) which they would claime aboue the moſt ſupreme, high &amp; Honourable meeting of the whole Kingdome? except it be, as ſo many Popes in their owne conceit, they would exemps themſelues altogether from all Saeculart power. And ſo the particular cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon theſe Miniſters were conuented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, was nothing elſe, but that they moſt ſeditiouſly, contemptuouſly, and in plaine diſdaine of his Maieſties Princely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and auctority Royal, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uene themſelues in a priuy conuenticle,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17390:15"/>
which they (wronging not onely his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie but the Church, as is already declared) prowdly, ſeditiouſly, and moſt falſly termed and maintaine to bee a generall aſſembly, notwithſtanding of his Highneſſe pleaſure and will ſignified to them and their Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries by miſsiues from the Commiſsioners of the generall aſſembly, that the meeting appointed at <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſhould deſert; And notwithſtanding of the prohibition by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Proclamation at the Mercate croſſe of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> and of our Letter ſent vnto them by the ſaid Sir <hi>Alexander Strayton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how vnlawful and vnduetifull their pretended excuſes are, being grounded as they alledge, vpon the feare which they conceiued of the ſuppreſsing of their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and ouerthrow of their diſcipline by the deſerting of that aſſembly once appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, let the world iudge; ſince not onely his Maieſties zeale and care for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Religion is well knowen to all men, but euen in ſpeciall his great loue to this people, in not intending to lay vpon them any new formes or ceremonies, is well
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17390:15"/>
manifeſted of late, by that Proclamation which his Maieſtie hath cauſed to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for clearing of all ſuch doubts out of his peoples heart: The tenour whereof followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="proclamation">
                        <p>
                           <hi>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas we haue euer ſince it</hi> pleaſed God to establiſh vs in the Imperiall Crowne of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> equally regarded the good of both the late Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> now happily vnited in our royall perſon in one Monarchie, euer minding to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and continue the good and lowable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and Lawes whereby each of them hath bene theſe many ages ſo worthily gouerned: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe ſome malitious ſpirits, enemies to that common tranquillitie ſo much deſired by vs (forgetting the many proofes both publique and priuate, which we haue giuen of that our gratious affection to that our natiue and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent countrey of <hi>North Britaine,</hi> of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, libertie and priuiledges whereof we haue at all occaſions taken ſo ſpeciall a patrociny, as the ſolemne aſsemblies of the Estates of <hi>South-Britaine,</hi>
                           <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17390:16"/>
and Commiſsioners from the Eſtates of both Kingdomes haue bene eye witneſſes) haue not bene aſhamed to labour to peruert the minds of our best affected Subiects, That whereas the inſolent and factious cariage of ſome of them hath merited most ſeuere ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduerſion, the would inſinuate themſelues in the commiſeration of the multitude, by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto them a glorious profeſſion of the maintayning of the Priuiledges and auctoriſed Diſcipline, intended by vs (as they affirme) to be vtterly ouerthrowne by a ſuddaine and vnſeaſonable laying vpon them at this preſent the Rites, Ceremonies, and whole Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call order establiſhed in the Church of this part of our Kingdome of <hi>Britaine.</hi> And as we haue euer carefully regarded how conuenient it is to maintaine euery Countrey in that forme of gouernment which is fittest and can beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the conſtitution thereof, and how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous alterations are without good aduice and mature deliberation, and that euen in matters of order of the Church, in ſome ſmall Ilands vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Dominions, we haue abſtained from ſuffering any alteration: So doubt we not, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17390:16"/>
our good Subiects will neuer be that credulous contrary to the knowen trueth, which hath euer appeared clearely in all our Actions, as to bee in any doubt, but as in all our proccedings we haue bene a Patrone of Religion and Iuſtice (two inſeparable conſeruers of all Monarchies,) So hath all our ſtudy and care euer bene to retrench and reforme all courſes that caried any preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to that integritie whereat wee haue euer aymed, and as by ſo many good Lawes ſet forth in our gouernment, Iuſtice hath attained to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other perfection and ſplendor, then it had in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our predeceſſours times, and with painefull and vnpleaſant buſineſſe, we haue in the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church taken away innumerable abuſes and corruptions, which if they had not bene remedied, had brought the puritie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in extreeme danger. Yet wee hope that none dare be ſo impudent as to affirme that by our Soueraigne power, or abſolute commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wee did the ſame (although wee enioyed our auctoritie a freely as any King or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the world) but as the diſeaſe of the Ciuill body was euer cured by the aduice of our three Eſtates, So the defects of the Church by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17390:17"/>
the helpe and counſell of thoſe who had greateſt intereſt in them, So as the preſumption of our by-gone actions in our adminiſtration, whiles we were preſent, the proofe of our fatherly care towards that part of our Kingdome ſince our reſidence here, may bee ſufficient to ſecure vs against all ſuch malitious calumniations. And how euer in rule of pollicie wee cannot but iudge it conuenient that two Eſtates ſo inſeparably conioyned, ſhould be drawen to as great confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in all things as the good of both may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; And that no Monarchy either in Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall pollicie hath yet attained to that perfection, that it needs no reformation, or that infinite occaſions may not ariſe whereupon wiſe Princes will foreſee for the benefit of their States, iuſt cauſe of alteration: Yet are wee and haue euer bene reſolued, not to make any ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine or haſty change in the gouernment of that part of our Kingdome, either Ciuill or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, but with graue aduice and conſent of our Eſtates, and the wiſeſt and beſt ſort of them whom it moſt properly concerns, much leſſe to trouble them with any vnneceſſary alteration of indifferent and Ceremoniall matters, and that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17390:17"/>
vpon ſuch foreſeene aduantages, and preuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of confuſion and euill to come, as the greateſt enemies of all Peace, obedience to Princes, and order in all gouernments ſhall not obtrude any inconuenient to the contrary. And as by Gods holy aſsiſtance, we haue drawen that part of our Kingdome out of infinite troubles, factions, and cruell barbarities, and reduced the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most borders and confines thereof to Gods obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and acknowledging of our Lawes; (an Eſtate neuer heard of before, ſince this Iland hath bene inhabited) So by the ſame diuine prouidence and our fatherly care ouer the whole Iland, we intend to tranſmit the ſame in good order, happy quietneſſe, and flouriſhing pollicie to that posteritie wherewith God hath bleſsed vs, and after them to the worlds end; Like as for the more verification of our Honourable intention, and to ſtop the mouthes of theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet ſpirits, rayſors of that falſe ſcandall of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, We haue appointed a generall aſsembly to be holden at <hi>Dundee</hi> the laſt Tueſday of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereat we expect reparation of thoſe diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in ſo farre as belongeth to their cenſure,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17390:18"/>
and to bee freed in time comming of all ſuch calumnies.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Giuen at our Honour of Hampton Court
<date>the xxvj. day of September <hi>1605.</hi> yeeres, In the third yeere of our raigne of <hi>Great Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>AFter the publication and imprinting of which Proclamation for indiction of a new aſſembly, it being ſtill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by vs that thoſe Miniſters remayning in Ward, vpon the ſight of their owne offences, with repentance for the ſame, ſhould humbly haue beſought his Maieſtie for pardon; yet did their obſtinacie ſtill continue, iuſtifying all their proceedings, as if they had committed no crime at all. Whereupon wee of his Maieſties Counſell, fearing the imputation of vnduetifull and vndiligent ſeruants, if by this our procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (vpon vaine hopes) of the triall of their offence, wee ſhould leaue it vnder the hazard of euery ones cenſure to be iudged by the multitude, according as their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conceits ſhould lead them; It was
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17390:18"/>
therefore thought meete to call them to their anſwere before vs, for that their moſt ſeditious, proud and contemptuous diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Maieſties commandement and prohibition. Being called vpon and all preſent, and enquired what defence they would make for themſelues, either to iuſtify or excuſe that their intollerable riot and contempt, firſt by ſpeach, and then by writ they gaue in the declinator following, as diſclayming themſelues altogether from any ſubiection to his Maieſtie, and his Counſell, making all their actions of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſort (by their owne interpretation) to be meere Spirituall, and that their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſecond of Iuly laſt at the Borough of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> was ſuch an eſſentiall Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall matter, warranted by Gods word, that therein they did no offence. And if any they had done, the Counſell of any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prince was no way to iudge them, but their owne aſſembly. A moſt lewd &amp; vaine poſition; It beeing a certaine and infallible Maxime in the Law, that their anſwer could not exceed the limits of the Libell and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17390:19"/>
And therefore they being onely accuſed at that time for ſuch a priuate and vnlawfull miſdemeanour, their declinator could not but directly deny his Maieſties auctoritie in that particular point. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue likewiſe ſet downe the tenour.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <p>MY Lords of ſecret Counſell; Pleaſeth your Lordſhips, The approbation or diſallowance of a generall Aſſembly, hath bene, and ſhould bee a matter and cauſe Spirituall, and alwayes cognoſced and iudged by the Church, as Iudges competent within this Realme. And ſeeing wee are called before your Lordſhips to heare and ſee it be found and declared, That wee haue very contemptuouſly and ſeditiouſly conuened and aſſembled our ſelues in a generall Aſsembly at <hi>Abeirdein</hi> the first Tewſday of Iuly laſt, and therefore the ſaid Aſsembly, and approbation thereof decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and declared to bee vnlawfull, as at more length is conteined in the ſummonds executed againſt vs thereanent; We in conſideration of the premiſſes, and other reaſons to be giuen by vs, haue iuſt cauſe to decline your Lordſhips
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17390:19"/>
iudgement, as no wayes competent in the cauſe aboue ſpecified. And by theſe preſents we ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter decline the ſame, Seeing wee are moſt willing to ſubmit our ſelues to the triall of the generall Aſsembly onely Iudge competent. By theſe preſents Subſcribed with our handes as followeth, At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the <hi>24.</hi> day of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the yeere of God <hi>1605.</hi> yeeres, <hi>Sic ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur:</hi> M. <hi>Iohn Forbes,</hi> M. <hi>Iohn Welſche,</hi> M. <hi>Ion Monro,</hi> M. <hi>Androe Duncane,</hi> M <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Stranchane,</hi> M. <hi>Iames Greig,</hi> M. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Forbes,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Yongſton,</hi> M. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than Inglis,</hi> M. <hi>Charles Ferme,</hi> M. <hi>Iames Irwing,</hi> M. <hi>Iohn Scharp,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Durie, Iohn Roſſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>THis Declinator being repelled, and they hauing vſed ſome other friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous defences with more loſſe of time then vttering of any matter, at laſt all being repelled, they were found to haue conuened moſt vnlawfully contrary to his Maieſties warrant and charge giuen to the contrary. And being returned to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall priſons, vpon aduertiſement giuen to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17390:20"/>
his Maieſtie of the whole proceedings in that Proceſſe before the Counſell, and of that proud preſumption of thoſe miniſters in propounding the ſaid Declinator, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to that Acte of Parliament made in Maij 1584. or any paine which they incurred by doing therof (which was, That any perſons either Spirituall or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall preſuming to decline the Iudgement of his Maieſtie and his Counſell in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whatſoeuer, ſhall incurre the paine of Treaſon) therefore his Maieſtie preſently ſent his Royall direction to his Counſell, that the ordinary courſe of Iuſtice accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes of this his Highneſſe Realme, ſhould proceede againſt thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who by the propounding of that Declinature had made a plaine denyall of their ſubiection to his Maieſtie, and of his Royall power and Authoritie ouer them. Whereupon ſixe of them being then in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within the Caſtle of <hi>Black-neſſe,</hi> were vpon the tenth of Ianuarie laſt brought to his Maieſties Borough of <hi>Lynlithgrw,</hi> and there preſented vpon panel before his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17390:20"/>
Iuſtice being the ordinarie Iudge of all matters Criminall, who had ioyned to him a great number of Noblemen and others of his Maieſties Counſell by his Highneſſe Commiſsion to aſsiſt the ſaid Iuſtice in that matter. And their Inditement being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon that firſt Statute made in Maij 1584. and vpon that their preſumptuous Fact in declining the Counſels iudgement when they were firſt brought to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, they were then demanded what they could ſay for themſelues before the matter ſhould paſſe to the tryall of a Iurie. And notwithſtanding that ſome of their owne brethren, vpon earneſt requeſt to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell hauing obtained Licence &amp; permiſsion to conferre with them and perſwade them to an humble ſubmiſsion and penitence; as likewiſe that their two principall Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators and Counſellors at Law not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perſwade them to this ſame courſe of humility wherein they dealt with them ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, did vpon their obſtinacie directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to pleade for them; and laſtly notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that they were publikely admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17390:21"/>
by the Iudge the very time of their ſtanding at the Barre, that putting off that maske ot wilfulneſſe (the onely thing which ſo blinded them from ſight of their owne follies) they would humbly craue his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties pardon, of whoſe great Clemencie, in caſe of their ſubmiſsion, all that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, had very great hopes and vttered great aſſurances: Yet ſuch was their malignant and indurate obſtinacie, as hardening their hearts againſt all theſe publicke and priuate perſwaſions and admonitions, they wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſiſted in iuſtifying their Actions; Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtill the aſsiſtance of ſo many Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours at Law as would ſtay with them: and the only thing they could alledge for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues why they ſhould not go to the tryall of an Aſsiſe, was, that the ſaid Statute of Maij 1584. was thereafter interpreted and limitted by a particular clauſe of a Statute made in 1592. wherein it is declared that the ſaid Act made in 1584. againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyning of the Counſels iudgement, ſhall no way be preiudiciall nor derogate any thing to the priuiledges which God hath giuen to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17390:21"/>
the Spirituall office-bearers in the Church, concerning heads of Religion, matters of Hereſie, Excommunication, collation or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of Miniſters, or any ſuch like eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall Cenſures, ſpecially grounded, and hauing the warrant of the word of God. And herein they doe alleadge that their meeting at that time in Aberdene being an eſſentiall cenſure, warranted by Gods word, they might lawfully decline the Counſels iudgement from taking cognition therein.</p>
            <p>Whereunto it was anſwered by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Aduocate of that his Highnes King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, That that their defence was to be repelled, becauſe the keeping of an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at a certaine time and place, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of another aſſembly of new, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Maieſties charge, and againſt the will and command of his Highneſſe Counſell of this Kingdome, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the diſaſſenting of his Maieſties Commiſsioner; much leſſe the keeping of that petty Conuenticle in the towne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdene</hi> that ſecond of Iuly laſt paſt, is not any head of Religion, matter of Hereſie,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17390:22"/>
Excommunication or eſſentiall Cenſure whatſoeuer; and ſo being no way vnder that limitation, muſt of all neceſsitie come vnder the generalitie of the former Statute in the 84. and they muſt haue incurred the paine of Treaſon for declining the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes Iudgement, being called to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vpon their contempt. And likewiſe in that ſame very clauſe of interpretation of the former Acte, howeuer it is declared that the ſayd Statute ſhall no way make deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Priuiledge that the office bearers in the Church haue giuen them concerning Religion, Hereſie and other Eccleſiaſticall cenſures (wherein his Maieſtie will be euer farre from the aſſuming vnto himſelfe any Papall and tyrannicall Authoritie ouer the expreſſe word of God) Yet doeth not that clauſe inferre ſuch a Priuatiue of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Souereigntie, as may denude him of that lawfull power which Chriſtian Kings haue ouer the Churches that are within their dominions. The matter going to the triall of an Aſsiſe, theſe ſixe are found guilty of high treaſon, and returned to their ſeuerall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17390:22"/>
priſons. And therfore as hereby this proud contempt and diſobedience of this ſmall handfull of miniſterie (to the very great griefe and ſorowe of all the well diſpoſed of that profeſsion in this kingdome) is clerely and truely ſet downe (that the ignorance thereof ſhould not be the occaſion of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking by any, of the moſt iuſt and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſes enforcing this hard proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them) ſo are the ſaid wilfull and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate perſons to be left to their iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their deſerts, whereunto they haue moſt contentiouſly conſtrained his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and in a maner extorted the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will.</p>
            <p>And neuertheleſſe ſince there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt whatſoeuer, but hath the owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers, no folly but by ſome patroniſed and allowed, and that vpon vaine curioſitie (notwithſtanding of their knowledge to the contrary) ſome will not ſticke to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Paradoxes and defend abſurdities, which (howſoeuer in matters friuolous and of no moment might be ouerſlipt &amp; not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded) yet in ſuch matters concerning his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17390:23"/>
Maieſties royall Auctoritie, and the excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or iuſtifying of high and proud con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts by any ſort or ranke of perſons, ſo farre ſhould wee of his Highneſſe counſell (in our duety and alleageance to our Prince and Souereigne) bee from any ſort of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe or negligence, as hereby wee haue thought meete to ſignifie his Maieſties ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall pleaſure and wil, that he doeth ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly command &amp; charge all his Highnes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this his Kingdome (of whatſoeuer ranke, place, calling, function or condition they be) that none of them preſume to take vpon them, either in publique or priuate, to murmure or call in queſtion in any ſort, this his Maieſties prerogatiue, and auctoritie Royall, or the lawfulnes of this proceeding againſt the ſaid Miniſters, or any way to make conſtructions, or to mis-interprete that acte of Parliament of the yeere 1584. concerning the declining of his Maieſties and his Counſels iudgment, otherwiſe then the ſame is made cleare and manifeſt by this preſent deciſion of the Iuſtice in the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the ſaid Miniſters, with certification to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17390:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them that ſhall contrauene the ſame, that they ſhalbe really puniſhed in the qualitie of ſeditious perſons, and wilfull contemners of his Maieſties moſt iuſt and lawfull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at Edinburgh</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the ſeuenth day of March, Jn the third yeere of his Maieſties raigne of great Britaine, France and Jreland.</hi> 1606.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17390:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17390:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
